Guide to the Sigmond and Lena Slonim Papers 1902-1981
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Sigmond and Lena Slonim Papers
1902-1981
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 735
Slonim, Sigmond.
1.5 Linear Feet of Shelf Space 3 boxes
Sigmond Slonim was born in Russia in 1878 and died in Duluth, Minnesota in 1981. He came to America in 1901 where he finished his education, culminating in a law degree from St. Paul College of Law in 1913. He practiced law until his retirement in 1957. This collection consists of personal and professional papers of Sigmond and Lena Slonim which were kept by their daughter, Ruth Slonim. Most of the materials are related to Sigmond Slonim.
Sigmond Slonim was born in Russia in 1878 and died in Duluth, Minnesota in 1981. He came to America in 1901 where he finished his education, culminating in a law degree from St. Paul College of Law in 1913. He practiced law until his retirement in 1957. He worked most often for the "underdog," including his efforts on behalf of children's welfare. He was active in the Farmer-Labor Association and even ran for office in that party. He was one of the founding members of the Saturday Lunch Club in Duluth, which met weekly to discuss issues of local, national, and international importance. He was also very involved in civic issues, including urban development and city planning. Slonim was a member of the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) and the Socialist Party of America.
Little biographical information is readily available for Lena Epstein Slonim (1885-1962), Sigmond Slonim's wife. She was also born in Russia, and as a young girl moved with her family to Minnesota. She earned a Bachelor of Philosophy degree from the University of Chicago in 1906; she also held a teaching certificate.
This collection consists of personal and professional papers of Sigmond and Lena Slonim which were kept by their daughter, Ruth Slonim, and donated to the Washington State University Libraries along with her own papers after her death.
Most of the materials are related to Sigmond Slonim. The personal correspondence includes incoming cards and letters, mainly from friends and family members. The professional correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing items, mostly related to Sigmond Slonim's law practice and political activism. The collection also includes other materials related to his political interests and activities, his law practice (two conscientious objector case files), and family finances. The "Sigmond Slonim writings" sequence consists primarily of autobiographical sketches and essays. Slonim described his early life and his family's experiences in Lithuania, including observations about political and social conditions for Jews in Russia, his travels through Europe prior to emigrating to the United States, and his life and involvement in progressive political causes after settling in Duluth, MN.
The materials are arranged in a single series.
This collection is open and available for research use.
This collection was received with the papers of Ruth Slonim, daughter of Sigmond and Lena Slonim, donated to the Washington State University Libraries by her estate (MS 2007-10).
Ruth Slonim papers (Cage 733)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Slonim, Sigmond -- Archives; Slonim, Lena -- Archives
Jews, Russian -- United States -- History.; Immigrants -- United States.
Russian Americans; Jewish Americans
- Correspondence, personal (incoming), 1947-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Sigmond Slonim correspondence, professional (incoming and outgoing), 1935-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Sigmond Slonim correspondence, miscellaneous (outgoing), 1947-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lena Epstein Slonim, circa 1900-1957. Notebook (mainly notes from academic courses); University of Chicago transcript; teaching certificate and miscellaneous items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Lena Epstein Slonim, legal and financial matters, 1929-1949. Includes items related to Lena Slonim and Epstein family members, particularly her father, Israel Epstein. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Temple Emmanuel, Duluth, MN, 1921-1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Slonim family financial and estate documents, 1949-1970s (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Clippings, 1920s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Sigmond Slonim miscellaneous (personal); includes political and social organization membership cards and naturalization certificate; 1907-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Farmer-Labor Association, 1920s-1940s. Includes Sigmond Slonim political campaign materials, news clippings, political platform documents, and miscellaneous items. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Sigmond Slonim campaign for State Senate, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Apartment and Home Taxpayers Association and Duluth Housing and Redevelopment Authority, 1958-1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Saturday Lunch Club (Duluth, MN) meeting minutes, membership lists, constitution, 1923-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Saturday Lunch Club addresses, 1946-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Saturday Lunch Club calendars, clippings, miscellaneous, 1960s-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Duluth Progress Association, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Juvenile Delinquency Bill and The Youth Conservation Act (State of Minnesota), 1946-1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Conscientous objector case, David Bullock, 1943-1956. Includes court documents, correspondence, and supporting documentation. (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
- Conscientous objector case, William Loeffert, 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Criminal syndicalism, 1917-1931 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Housing Code and Urban Renewal, 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Child welfare, 1947-1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous (professional), 1933-1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Sigmond Slonim writings (primarily autobiographical sketches and essays, along with opinion essays about political and social issues), 1930s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 1-6)